Finding Aid for Vietnam Veterans of America, Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1973-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vietnam Veterans of America, Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.) records 1973-2011 1980-1997
Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.)
87396 Be 2
This collection includes material regarding the activities of the Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc., Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.). Some members of this group have also been involved in the Vietnam Veterans of America (VVA) State of Michigan Council, as well as the Michigan Veterans Trust Fund and Vietnam Monument Commission so materials from these groups have also been included in this collection.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the organization (donor no. 7420 ) in 1987. Additions were received in 2001 and September 2013.
The record group is open to research.
Vietnam Veterans of America, Chapter 9, Detroit, an affiliated chapter of the national organization Vietnam Veterans of America Inc., is a service and fraternal organization of men and women who served in the U.S. Military during the Vietnam era. Membership is open to all veterans who served on active duty during the period August 5, 1964 to May 5, 1975 or who served in Vietnam at any time. About 90 percent of Chapter 9 members are Vietnam combat veterans.
Originally organized ca. 1978-1979 as Vietnam Veterans of Michigan, Chapter 9 was incorporated as a non profit corporation with the State of Michigan in April 1981. Chapter 9 membership was about 650 in 1987, making Detroit the largest local VVA chapter in the country. It has played an influential role in the national organization, sending several members to serve as national officers and hosting the 1985 national convention.
Chapter 9 sponsors a variety of individual and group counseling programs for Vietnam-era veterans, with special emphasis on post-traumatic stress disorder, agent orange, drug and alcohol abuse, employment, and Veterans Administration claims assistance. Other chapter activities include lobbying for legislation beneficial to veterans, conducting public education programs in schools, churches, and civic organizations, and participating in community development projects, particularly in the Woodward Avenue neighborhood of its headquarters and service center.
Keith King, the donor of this collection, was a founding, and life, member of VVA's Chapter 9. He has served three consecutive terms as the Chairman of the State of Michigan Council and State Commissioner of the Michigan Vietnam Monument Commission. He was also appointed a Trustee of the Michigan Veterans Trust Fund and served as the Chairman of the Board of Trustees from 1996-1998 and 2001-2002.
The Michigan Veterans Trust Fund is a program under the Department of Military and Veterans Affairs that provides assistance to veterans or their families facing temporary financial hardship. Some Vietnam Veterans of America representatives serve on the board of this program.
The Vietnam Monument Commission was formed for the purpose creating memorial monument for Vietnam veterans in the state of Michigan. This commission began its work in 1990 and through fundraising efforts and design competitions aided in the creation of a monument built in Lansing in 2001.
This collection has five series: Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. Chapter 9 (Detroit), Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc., Michigan Veterans Trust Fund, Vietnam Monument Commission, and Audio and visual material. Records in this collection include administrative documents, Vietnam Veterans of American national convention materials, and VVA chapter newsletters and publications.
Subjects:
Michigan Veterans Trust Fund.; Veteran Monument Commission of Michigan.; Veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc.; Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.); Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Monuments--Michigan.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Veterans.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Veterans' organizations.; Vietnam Monument Commission of Michigan.; Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc.; Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.); Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Monuments--Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Memorial Day.; Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.); War memorials--Michigan.
Contributors:
King, Keith.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Vietnam Veterans of America-Detroit Chapter
  The America, Chapter 9, Detroit series includes the chapter bylaws and articles of incorporation, financial records, history of the chapter, an index of members, and chapter newsletters from Chapter 9, as well as other Michigan chapters. There are separate sets of minutes for the General Membership meeting (October 1981-January 1987), the Board of Directors (September 1981-December 1986), and the Executive Board (September 1981-September 1983 and May-August 1985). There is some information regarding Keith King and his veterans affairs involvement and campaign for national VVA president in 1985.
  - 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1989-1998 (Box 1)
  - "Aftermath" (Box 1)
    (VVA chapter 9 news publication)
  - Aftermath, Aftermath II 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - "Aftermath Update" 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Agent Orange 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - The AMVET Story Continues... 1992 (Box 1)
    (Television production created for Veterans, produced by B.J. Mercado and son Charles Mercado)
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Articles of incorporation and tax documents 1981-1991 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors
    - 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - Meetings
      - 1982 (Box 1)
      - 1986 (Box 1)
  - Business cards undated (Box 1)
  - Chapter anniversaries 2001, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Chapter guidebook undated (Box 1)
  - Chapter newsletters
    - Chapter newsletter-L.Z. MOTOWN Review 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - 9-Detroit 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      (Detroit, MI)
    - 18-Kent County 1983 (Box 1)
      (Kent County, MI)
    - 30-Lansing 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      (Lansing, MI)
    - 73-Holland area 1982-1990 (Box 1)
      (Holland, MI)
    - 93-Kalamazoo 1983-1990 (Box 1)
      (Kalamazoo, MI)
    - 180-Sault Ste. Marie (Box 1)
      (Sault Ste. Marie, MI)
    - 211-Traverse area 1987-1991 (Box 1)
      (Traverse City, MI)
    - 250-Saginaw 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      (Saginaw, MI)
    - 267-Dearborn 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      (Dearborn, MI)
    - 287-Lapper County 1990 (Box 1)
      (Lapper County, MI)
    - Miscellaneous 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    (Newspaper clippings)
  - Committee to Elect Keith King president of VVA 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - July 1982-March 1983 (Box 1)
    - October 1985-June 1986 (Box 1)
    - July 1986-May 1987 (Box 1)
  - Election report 2008 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Flight of the Phoenix Vet Center and Agent Orange 1980 (Box 1)
  - History 2006 (Box 1)
  - Keith King
    - Miscellaneous 1975-1986 (Box 1)
      (includes cassette tape of radio interview and a photograph)
    - Veteran affairs involvement 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - VVA national president campaign 1985 (Box 2)
  - Legislative File 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Membership
    - Lists 1995-2001 (Box 2)
    - Pending 1996 (Box 2)
  - Membership committee report 1983 (Box 2)
  - Minutes
    - Board of Directors
      - October 1981-September 1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
    - Executive Board September 1981-September 1983, May-August 1985 (Box 2)
    - General membership meetings October 1981-January 1987 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1985-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - VVA 1985 National Convention Planning Committee (Box 2)
  - Membership index 1980-1998 (Box 2)
    (In an index card box)
  - Newspaper articles 1984-1997 (Box 3)
  - "Our Vietnam Generation" film 2009-2011 (Box 3)
  - Photographs undated (Box 3)
    (Ted Dzlengeleweski)
  - Photograph undated (Box 3)
  - Press releases 1982-1984 (Box 3)
  - POWs/MIAs 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Prisoner of War-Missing in Action (POW-MIA) recognition day 1990 (Box 3)
    (Friday, September 21, 1990)
  - Regulations and Procedures 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Senator Carl Levin 1997 (Box 3)
  - Special Committees 1985 (Box 3)
  - Suspension and re-instatement 1998 (Box 3)
  - The Wall 25th anniversary parade sponsorship information and "Thank You for Serving" DVD 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Vietnam veteran center in Detroit 1983-1985 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous printed material
    - Chicago "Welcome Home" Vietnam veteran parade 1986 (Box 3)
    - Department of Veterans Affairs 1990 (Box 3)
    - Michigan veteran Agent Orange news articles 1986 (Box 3)
    - National Geographic magazine May 1985 (Box 3)
      (Pg. 565 features a picture with Vietnam Veterans of America at the Wall monument in D.C.)
    - Programs 1982-1986 (Box 3)
    - Vietnam magazine, April and June, 1990 (Box 3)
    - VietNow newsletter -- West Michigan chapter, 1990 (Box 3)
- Vietnam Veterans for America, Inc.
  The Vietnam Veterans of America, Inc. series includes national convention materials from six conventions, newspaper articles, the "Veteran" national newsletter, a directory, and a report to members regarding legal, constitutional, and internal issues. The State of Michigan Council documents contain meeting minutes, material on POWs/MIAs and women veterans, as well as documents collected by Marilyn Edgerton-Mallard, who served on this council, was a member of the VVA Chapter 9, and was involved in work related to women veterans.
  - National
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - Agent Orange undated (Box 3)
    - Assistance fund and Vetconnect 2006 (Box 3)
    - Chapter directory, Board members, revenue, and communications 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - D.C. Vietnam veterans memorial 1982 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1982-1995 (Box 3)
    - National Convention
      - 1985-Detroit (Box 4)
      - 1987-District of Columbia (Box 4)
      - 1995-Houston, Texas (Box 4)
      - 1997-Kansas City, Kansas (Box 4)
      - 1999-Anaheim, California (Box 4)
      - 2005-Reno, Nevada (Box 4)
    - Newspaper articles 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - Report on legal, constitutional, and internal issues 2005 (Box 3)
    - Report to members 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Veteran"
      (National VVA news publication)
      - 1983-1986 (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Veteran reader survey 1985 (Box 3)
    - Women veterans' project-steering committee 1982 (Box 3)
  - State of Michigan Council
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - 1990 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - 1982-2006 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1990 (Box 5)
    - Council nominations to Michigan Veterans Trust Fund (MVTF) 1992 (Box 5)
    - Incorporation and Agent Orange death 1984-1986 (Box 5)
    - Marilyn Edgerton-Mallard
      - 1983-1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Letters to legislators 1982 (Box 5)
      - Veteran survey questionnaires 1982 (Box 5)
      - Women veterans 1988-1991 (Box 5)
    - Master list of state chapters 1996 (Box 5)
    - Meeting minutes 1986-1990 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Agent Orange commission
      - 1987 (Box 5)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1982-1987 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1986-1989 (Box 5)
    - Prisoner of war committee of Michigan 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - POW/MIA 1973-1992 (Box 5)
    - Report on activities1982-1984 (Box 5)
    - Veteran women's memorial project 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Women veterans committee 1987 (Box 5)
- Michigan Veterans Trust Fund
  The Michigan Veterans Trust Fund series contains directories, documents from the Board of Trustees, laws regarding the trust fund, as well as audit and annual reports.
  - Annual report and performance appraisal
    - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Guidebook 1993 (Box 5)
  - Audit report 1990-1995 (Box 5)
  - Board of Trustees
    - 1994 (Box 5)
    - 1995 (Box 5)
  - Board policy manual and fact sheet 1996 (Box 6)
  - Budget concerns 1995 (Box 6)
  - Commanders' Group directory 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - County committee positions 1996 (Box 6)
  - Directory
    - 1986-1987 (Box 6)
    - 1994 (Box 6)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Keith King-Chairman 1996 (Box 6)
  - Michigan veteran laws for trust fund 1996 (Box 6)
  - Procedural memorandums 1990 (Box 6)
  - Status update and Vietnam Veterans of America (VVA) representatives 1995-1996 (Box 6)
- Vietnam Monument Commission
  The Vietnam Monument Commission contains material that documents the process of the commission as it worked towards its goal of creating a monument in Michigan. Included are paper and radio advertisement materials, communications with advertising companies, and fundraising conducted by the commission. There are also documents about the competition the commission held to determine a design for the monument, the monument proposal, and the dedication of the monument in 2001.
  - 1992, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Advertisements
    - 1993 (Box 6)
    - 1996 (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Advertising and fundraising
    - 1992 (Box 6)
      (includes photographs)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 6)
    - 1994 (Box 6)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 6)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 6)
    - 1997 (Box 6)
    - Bozell Worldwide, Inc. 1997 (Box 6)
    - CME 1993 (Box 6)
    - T-shirt inventory 1991-1993 (Box 6)
  - Annual report 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - Brochures 1996-2002 (Box 6)
  - Communications plan 1993 (Box 6)
  - Completion 2001-2004 (Box 6)
  - Corporate sponsorship 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, memorandums, and administrative materials 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - County captain materials
    - 1994 (Box 7)
    - 1996 (Box 7)
  - Dedication 2001 (Box 7)
  - Design competition 1992 (Box 7)
  - Facts and press releases 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - Fundraising
    - 1992 (Box 7)
    - 1993 (Box 7)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - Activities 1992, 1 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 7)
      (includes floppy disk)
  - Keith King-public relations chair and commissioner 1993-1995 (Box 7)
  - Logo ideas undated (Box 7)
  - Media advisory board meetings 1992 (Box 7)
  - Media kit and timeline 2001 (Box 7)
  - Meeting agenda January 30, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Memorial act and monument resolution 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Michigan personnel who died in war 1992, 1 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 7)
    (Includes floppy disk)
  - Michigan Vietnam veteran memorials and monument 1995 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1992-1997 (Box 7)
  - Monument news articles and corrections 1993-1994 (Box 7)
  - Monument plans 1995 (Box 7)
  - Monument proposal 1995 (Box 7)
    (submitted by Growth Design Corporation)
  - New strategy planning documents 1996 (Box 7)
    (submitted by The Romona Group)
- Audio and Visual Materials
  The Audio and Visual Materials series includes cassette tapes with recorded stories and interviews, some from the radio. Some of the recordings are of Keith King, Michigan resident and the Vietnam War veteran who collected a large portion of the Vietnam Veterans of America, Chapter 9 (Detroit, Mich.) records collection. The VHS tapes and DVDs contain recordings of the "AMVET story continues...", and about Vietnam monuments. Ephemera including buttons, bumper stickers, and pins are also in this series.
  - Cassette tapes
    - The Untold Story Nam-Tribute to Nam by Tom Clark (Box 7)
    - Sunday Spotlight (Box 7)
    - 104.3 Keith King 11/11/1997 (Box 7)
    - 104.3 Memorial Day PSA Veterans Memorial 5/1995 (Box 7)
    - Jasinia/Donovan/Engler Interview (Box 7)
    - Vietnam Memorial by Campbell Mithun Esty(CME) 2/19/1993 (Box 7)
    - 2649 Memorial Day 8/29/1997 (Box 7)
  - VHS-DVD
    - Vietnam Monument Commission (Box 7)
      (VHS)
    - "AMVET Story Continues" Chapter 58 taped 10/29/1992 (Box 7)
    - "AMVET Story Continues" Chapter 76 taped 07/10/1993 (Box 7)
    - Tape of news of the unveiling (Box 7)
    - Veterans Support Foundation 2009 PSA's (Box 7)
      (CD)
    - The Wall 25 years Anniversary Parade November 10, 2007. A production of Veterans Support Foundation 2009 (Box 7)
      (DVD)
  - Ephemera undated (Box 7)